I wanted to first ask you guys how are
you doing how's everything how are you
and and your families and you know
without anything personal just what's
going on over there in Toronto so I'm
doing well as all the people I love and
care about including Chris and there's
no in-person classes at the University
of Toronto so I've been switching
everything over to virtual the
psychology department the department
physically closed on Friday I fully
expect that the entire University will
be physically closed as a month beer
Tuesday I think they're trying to keep
it open as long as possible for
libraries and whatnot but I expect that
that's gonna end
shortly because the premiere has asked
us to go into pretty much lockdown so
and the University of course being
publicly funded a university will follow
what the premier says so I fully expect
that that will be it when what's gonna
happen I don't know going forward I've
already received one email indicating
that the courses that I'm supposed to
teach in May and June
nothing official has been said but I
should plan for them to be done totally
virtually as well so that's what's
happening sort of professionally and
personally what's happening virtually is
I've done a couple of talks with Jordan
Hall around kovat 19 and issues around
it around rationality and faith and then
starting Monday I'm going to offer a
live streaming free meditation course
for people so that they will be able to
go come on and I'll take them through
like a 10 to 12 week meditation course
when I know it'll be mornings 9:30
Eastern Standard Time 9:30 to 10:00 I'll
usually teach
probably a new principal Monday and
Thursdays and then in between we'll also
just meet regularly and sit together so
that's something I'm gonna try and do to
help people out and Peter Lindbergh and
I are also putting together he's trying
to revise some sort of a virtual stoah
they've got some of the most famous
Stoics involved current Stoics I mean it
was not like we resurrected anybody and
no Seneca Seneca will be yeah so we're
gonna be offering that for people as a
place where they can go also to well try
to cultivate some in-person stoicism to
give them a way of dealing with some of
the extra strains that this is putting
on their lives so that's that's sort of
where I'm at right now
hmm so how about you Christian is there
anything you want to add to that no not
really I'm also fine my me and mine are
fine so far um we've been very fortunate
I think comparably here next to much of
the rest of the world I think and
because I've been I've been off work for
some months anyway so my day-to-day life
hasn't changed a whole lot although I'm
learning that there's a difference
between like elective solitude and
solitude by ordinance the activities on
the ground aren't all that different
that feeling is a little bit different
it has it's not quite an ordinance yet
here but it's that's just shy of that
it's like we haven't been ordered to
remain cloistered in our homes but but
everything is as John said everything's
more or less shuttered so you really you
don't have a lot of options if you want
to venture out anyway but yeah I would
say so far so good so far so good
yeah how are you doing Andrew Oh
something first I do person I were both
talking just before you came into the
room that we were actually very pleased
with how our both our federal and
provincial governments are handling this
we're very happy about that and we think
they're doing an excellent job mmm
that's good to know
yeah about me personally well it's very
interesting because I'm an overworked
underpaid teacher I would say so in the
past
months I've been working crazily doing a
lot of classes and also doing this kind
of thing so so I've been overworked
basically and a little bit burnt out and
so now I'm on total lockdown I've been
we've been on total lockdown for about a
week here in France and luckily we moved
last year to the edge of Paris so we
have a little garden so I'm feeling like
I'm very lucky compared to a lot of my
friends and colleagues who are stuck in
little apartments in Paris and they
can't leave without a piece of paper
basically no they they need to have a
piece of paper to say I'm going to the
store or I'm going for a jog or
something like that so it's very extreme
here and it seems we're on the up curve
so it's just getting worse in terms of
numbers but so there's this extreme
contrast between how wonderful my life
is right now I'm here with my family and
I'm doing I'm working remotely like like
you John and I I'm doing you know
physical work every morning and I'm
feeling much healthier than I have in a
long time actually and the grim picture
outside and my neighbor who's elderly
and just had a stroke and and it's very
odd he can't really we're not supposed
to go and talk to her and so well
usually we have a relationship so so so
there's it's a very very extreme
contrast between me right now feeling
like I'm living my life like I would
want to be living my life really almost
in a retreat like a Buddhist retreat
with my family and and then the extreme
situation outside yeah so that's Andrew
I just I'm just this is a practical
curiosity but I've heard of that I've
heard I know this is true of Italy I
didn't know that it was also true of
France that you need some kind of you
need effectively a permission slip to go
out and carry on your business what what
does that mean like where do you get
that is you you can find it on the
internet and you have to print it out
and it has to have
date on it so we've had our groceries
delivered so I haven't even gone out and
done that yet actually but but so I
guess you you can change the date each
time you go go out and you have to say
why you're going out if you're going out
to walk the dog or go for a jog you have
to be six meters away from other people
six meters something is something like
that maybe I've got that wrong I could I
could have a but but you're supposed to
really keep a distance from everybody
I'm not allowed to go out with my family
for a walk for example I can go out
alone I can go for a jog and I could do
exercise or go for a walk but but but
again I'm in a little village so I'm not
in the heat of the the the the heat of
the thing which a lot of my friends in
Paris are and I can kind of I can feel
that from them that it's very intense I
think being stuck in a small apartment
would be would be pretty hard yeah you
know so I read your papers your paper
today much too quickly i'm gonna i'm
going to reread it in more more detail
here it's called
gnosis in the second person responding
to the meaning crisis in the Socratic
quest of authentic dialogue so what
struck me in the end is is and please
correct me if I'm wrong if I've
misunderstood something because I this
is a big overview so this is about dialo
goes right yeah and you outline sort of
five dimensions of dialogue OHS and one
is the let's say person to person which
is the horizontal dimension of dialogue
us me talking to you and then the
vertical dimension which is about
talking to to being about questioning
yourself and/or your existence I guess
or being itself and then you talk about
how that
but that moves into something a third
dimension which is related to the eye
maybe the ID though in some level that
something is created out of this
dialogue hmm right
and I and then the fourth dimension is
that moves into time and then the fifth
dimension is a kind of timelessness that
results and so so I like this whole
model I think it's very very beautiful
and I wondered if you could just go into
detail and flush it out a bit so I'll uh
I'll start Chris and I'll probably
tag-team a lot because our thinking on
this paper is deeply symbiotic I think
one thing is to perhaps it would be
useful to keep a distinction in hand
that we could refer to throughout which
is dialogo cesare the process that's
being realized and dialectic is the
psycho technology that people can learn
and practice in order to try and realize
the process and try to cause it to be
instantiated in a dialogue and so part
of what we're trying to do in the paper
is to figure out as you mentioned the
the dimensions both phenomenological and
functional of D logos as a process and
we're also starting to that of course
has merit in its own right we're also
doing that also because we're trying to
figure out from the phenomenology and
the functionality what the psycho
technology should look like what should
dialectic look like what are some of the
features that should be put into
practice and the hope is the oral hope
from the paper is if we can work back
from the phenomenology and functionality
of the Ilocos into sort of reverse
engineering the dialectic we can put
that potentially into a deep dialogue
and I choose that term intentionally a
deep dialogue with what we see in
Socratic practice within the Platonic
dialogues and the Neoplatonic traditions
as a way of then putting all of that
into dialogue with
what's happening right now with the
emergence of both psycho technologies
like guy sense talks circling or you
know Atwood Rocha is empathy circling or
Peter Lindbergh's
aunty debate these new practices and
their attempts to tap into the
collective intelligence of distributed
cognition and so if we can
reverse-engineer dialectic put it into
contact with the historical scholarship
of platonic dialectic take that whole
thing and put it into dialogue with
these emerging practices in which people
are seeking to reformulate Andry vivify
dialogue so that it can be a means by
which people can cultivate wisdom in a
deep sense then we think what we can do
is help to bring philosophy ax the
cultivation of wisdom into these
emerging practices because I generally
see although I have great value and
appreciation and I participate in these
practices I'm not just an outsider of
great value and appreciation for things
like circling and I'm in constant
communication with guys and Stein and
guy actually sanctions this in a
positive sense on what I'm about to say
I see these practices as largely lacking
the integration with philosophy ax and
that maybe means if can i interject a
little bit of lacking in thinking
lacking in a Nigerian yeah I think
you're in when we what Heidegger means
by thinking yeah this is almost taboo in
in these kind of circles we're supposed
to have a we're supposed to work on our
feeling somatic experiences and then on
the other hand so there's this divide
between the somatic experience and the
somatic Romanticism yeah there's an
intellectualization and extreme sort of
empiricism on one hand and extreme sort
of experience on the other am i give you
very much very much I think that's right
I think there's kind of yeah there's
kind of a Cartesian intellectualism
that's often the presentation of
propositional argumentation or there is
sort of it like I call it the semantic
romantic moment a system where somehow
by sort of exploring our somatic States
we will accrue to the good life that's
not to say that there isn't a lot of
value in mindfulness and reception you
know I buy and hold all of that but I I
agree what's missing and I think you put
your finger on it well in a lot of these
practices where we're trying to
communicate and even commune if by that
we mean that the connectedness and
intimacy between people is also valued
what's missing and all in a lot of these
practices is like I said is but how do
they how do they help us cultivate
wisdom both individually and
collectively in a way that's seriously
needed for addressing the meaning crisis
no no no let Chris speak well that was
pretty comprehensive John the only thing
I would add to it is that in order to
affect the convergence between the more
the sort of the discwizard of dimension
of it and what we might call the more
characterological dimension of it is
that's why we've invoked the Socratic
exemplar positive your vocabulary always
just knocks me off my feet what is dis
quiz ative please discwizard of meaning
the process of disquisition meaning sort
of the the explication the the
discussion for the purpose of
explication ratiocination that kind of
thing that that sort of a guys know that
yeah yeah um so I mean the reason that
Socrates is such a choice symbol or
symbol only for us is precisely because
the Socratic dialogue goes combines the
dramaturgical dimensions of in the
interactivity of the process right the
actual felt somatization of the process
right the dimension of it that's played
through and dramatized and enacted and
then the dimension of it that then
regather zazz as a as a process of of
what we might call reasoning or
rationing right and so because because
Socrates as a symbol is both a entreats
us to both at once he entreats us both
to the to the the discourse for the
purpose of insight and discourse for the
purpose of for a personal transformation
those two are then bundled in the
process of dialogue Louis right because
you have what we called or what right
called the sensibility transcendence
between persons the disclosure the
disclose the social disclosure that
avails insights about one another and
then you have in in between the interest
to seize of that process you have the
ontological disclosure the thing that
seems to avail more of reality and that
they're bundled together and Socrates
because of the nature of the symbol
because of his countenance he tends to
provoke both of those states at once
because Socrates sort of stands Socrates
is both a personal and impersonal
mystery right and we don't know who that
somehow who knowing who Socrates is
isn't just knowing who Socrates is it's
also knowing who we are and knowing who
we are isn't just knowing who we are
it's knowing what what what the world is
writ large and all of these things seem
to constantly together in this credit
symbol and that's why he's like the
prism through which all of this then
opens so that's why we've dropped him I
mean it's not exactly an ingenious move
Socrates has been this for a long long
time too many people we've dropped him
into the middle of this because he's so
he's he's an emissary and an exemplar
for it at same time right so he's a
bridge and he's sort of a bridge between
the per the personal and the impersonal
going back and forth and he also
transcends both the personal and the
impersonal
well he variously presents himself as a
tip-offs not belonging to any category
and as Mattacks ooh somehow between the
human and the divine and so he he
consciously or at least through in
plato's dialogue identifies with those
two those two you know buying the symbol
long relationships yet the binding
together the he see he sort of sits
between our normal categories of
identity for human beings and as I said
he sits between the human
devine and therefore he can bind both of
those together raquel skiing has really
good book Heidegger's Platonism talks
about why Socrates in the dialogic form
are actually inseparable this goes back
- Lear mocker and Slagle from the
presentation of what of Plato's view of
of the cultivation of wisdom and the
baby the basic idea is and it's it I
think it actually comports a very well
conversion with the argument that Chris
and I are making but trying to get
dialogue activating and integrating all
the four kinds of knowing in that what
we see in the dialogue you need some you
need three things you need argumentation
obviously mm-hmm in order to do as Chris
said provoke those kinds of profound
insight it has to be a kind of an
argument ation directed towards the
affordance of aporia right that that way
you're you're forced to step back and
wonder in a profound way to call
yourself into question and think about
Heidegger we are the beings whose aporia
is means a sort of a state of unknown
buck City yeah that's like a net right
yeah deep deep perplexity an epidemic
precipice beyond okay so he pushes you a
little bit towards the precipice and
then you stand back and you experience
wonder and everything comes into
question and therefore you you you
actually identify with what Heidegger
would call design you identify with that
aspect that seems to be central to human
beings how we are the beings whose
beings are in question and that gives us
a privileged kind of access in our being
not in a not in our self or oh yeah but
a nurse analogy but but beyond that not
yeah not just in our propositional
thoughts but in in that deeper kind of
thing we're talking about earlier the
thinking and so that of course it is
centrally are the argumentation but you
but what you you don't have just a
competition of arguments right in the
dialogue you also the competition of
ways of life separate you have to
represent a way of life he represents
the unexamined life that is right sorry
the examined life is living in
competition so you're not only having
arguments in competition you need to see
ways of life in competition
with each other hey yeah continue your
thought I just will make the third point
and you can choose how you wish to
respond and so Socrates exemplifies the
competition between arguments that is
supposed to induce wonder and the
insight that Chris mentioned he's
supposed to you can't do this with
argumentation you have to in order to
represent the competition between ways
of life you have to rely on drama that's
so the das be embodied all right yeah
you have to have that and right so how
are you gonna get argument and drama
together you need dialogue and then the
next thing you need right is you need
you need Socrates represents aspiration
he represents our relationship to our
sacred second self he represents a call
to transformation and transcendence
right and that call to to I mean that's
another reason why has to be symbolic
for us that call to self transcendence
right that's there has to be you need a
form of thinking that's inherently woven
with symbol it has to it has to both
reach you where you are but draw you
beyond where you are it has to do a dues
it has to it has to be the Midwife for
you and so the dialogue is also the way
in which you represent that aspirational
relationship right it's in the back and
forth between you the interlocutors and
Socrates that you can see the
aspirational movement taking place the
dialogue they that the fact that the
dialogues are like they're non
completable they're open-ended they're
often emergent is exactly required for
representing what Plato is trying to
talk about so the so I'm trying to say
there's these three deep ways in which
Socrates exemplifies the necessity of
dialogue for the cultivation of wisdom
mmm okay
you were talking about the examined life
in the unexamined life okay yes and so
as you were saying that what came to me
right now is the event that we're all
experiencing which seems to be in the
background of all of our discussions
even if we're talking about
you know philosophical high abstract
philosophical things Oh
and so so I want I want to somehow make
a bridge to what's going on in the world
right now and and the examined life and
and what that means in the face of this
extraordinary thing that's happening in
the world coronavirus or whatever and
how this can and also how to how this
can help us in terms of this dialogue
owes in terms of making life more
meaning through dialogue owes how can we
relate that to our actual experience
right now you do you have anything to
say well I do I want to give I want to
relate a quick story and it will
directly concerns Chris and that way I
can segue to Chris yes I wanna hear what
he was just because Chris and I have
been talking about this at length and I
want I want him to take over a little
bit on this but I had another meeting
with virtual meeting somebody was
interviewing me about the meeting crisis
and we were talking and we were talking
at one point and I said I want to be
very careful with the language and he
said and he picked up on that knee and
he's like you know that he really liked
that and and then he and then I said you
know you know and then I pointed to
Chris and Chris is gift his great gift
for being both you know capable of a
precision of expression that is at the
same time beautiful and beauty is one of
the ways in which we aspire right this
is a plutonic idea and then you know
that I pointed to Chris about that
because Eric I was trying to say how
that precision and beautification of
thought is so needed and he had this
responsible spontaneous and beautiful he
said of course I would he said this
literally he said I would rather die
than not talk like that and I'm using
this example because it's very pertinent
to what we're talking about right now
he's in the middle of this crisis and he
says to me right he says it very since
earth I'd rather died and not be
to talk that way and then I said to him
that's you I said you know you've said a
lot but that's the Socratic moment for
me that's what you that's where you get
it not in thought but you get it in
yourself like you're being right that
the unexamined life is not worth living
and there's something about that and you
know and notice that the context the
language he used and the context in
which Socrates offered that Socrates was
facing death the person that I was
talking to he is you know he's he's
facing the situation you're referring to
Andrew and that's that comes out from
him naturally and spontaneously there
right and so there there there is
obviously you know there's a sense in
which we're jumping up and down Maslow's
hierarchy of needs right now and people
have to take care of their survival but
there's a point at which right there's a
point at which people also need a
meaning to a difficult difficult
situation in fact in the most difficult
of situations the most threatening of
situations they are willing to put mere
survival at risk in order to try and
maintain an examined and meaningful life
period as I said Chris came readily to
my mind about that deep connection him
readily to my lips
about that deep connection between the
capacity for making meaning and that
ability to revivify and you know empower
the the entirety of one psyche yeah
please speak to that Chris because I
think that's my experience of both you
guys actually in and that's why I want
to talk to you I think you both have
that drive that that kind of almost
monomania which which which wouldn't
wouldn't wouldn't couldn't bear on some
level to be living a life that wasn't
that didn't have authenticity but also a
kind of striving towards beauty at the
same time
sorry to keep talking Chris please say
something well I think I kind of hot at
the collar I thank you John and I don't
it's definite I don't feel equals those
estimations so maybe I'll just glide
over them I'm touched by it I just don't
know what to say to it I think so I
think there are some interesting things
happening that I've been noticing both
personally and then in personally I was
telling John that I had I had a strange
episode maybe a week ago or so where I
felt there's really no other way to put
it I just sort of felt the gulf open up
beneath me and the sense of futility and
I and I mean I'm a damn it this
attribution I think at the time I think
what I think now was a Mitch and
misattribution of any number of personal
failings or personal doubts and I think
what it actually was is it had something
more to do with the Supra personal
nature of what's going on right now but
I was effectively enclosed by feelings
of futility that were tera lytic like a
torpor just something that I couldn't
move from I remember what I went in
three hours on a three hour walk just to
try and shake it off and didn't manage
to do it and I just sort of lingered for
a couple of days and then slowly over
time it unwound enough for me to regain
some ability and to get back into
activity but I was puzzled by that
because I never I never I never
experienced something that I found such
a difficult time sourcing that seems so
diffuse whose locus was nowhere and
everywhere at the same time and the
diffuseness of that feeling is precisely
what marks this crisis it's a property
of virulence in general and because of
that virulence is such an easy host for
meaninglessness just as the BIOS is host
for a virus right it affects the analogy
of meaninglessness precisely because we
can't source it properly
and it reminds me of I think it was
Hegel who talks about the distinction
between truth and certainty and that the
scientism of the president has collapsed
them together and I think what may
happen now and potentially this is you
know some kind of Kairat if you are
talking about this John as a kind of
chaotic opportunity then perhaps it is
we might hope so that with the ebbing of
certainty comes a renewed interest in
truth yes in a way that can effectively
dissociate itself from the from the from
what I think is ultimately an erroneous
synonym 'ti right they are not the same
thing fundamentally they cannot be and
while that distinction might not
completely disappear as a consequence of
the crisis at least there might be some
tremors sort of laid to the foundations
of that misconception and if that
happens enough for us to take notice
it's as that like it's as though we're
citing a familiar script and we recite
it like an epistrophe we recite it over
and over and over again but then all of
a sudden it's like a seizure and there's
pausing script a pause long enough for
us to hear a moment of silence through
it if like is the credit this little
it's like a Socratic aporia in a
repetitive aporia and if we can if we
can get a foot across the threshold of
the aporia and hold it in place long
enough to listen to listen into the
silence into the silence of the suppori
a' then there might be something in
behind and in between that silence that
becomes something life-affirming and
life-giving I mean you're but I'm not
but you're both or are or were at some
point Buddhists
I can't help think of Shunyata alright
groundlessness that comes to mind
um just groundlessness which is another
sort of translation of Shunyata so I was
thinking right right right and so but
then the transmutation of that empty
vacuous nothingness into the stream now
the the sness of the you know is that's
a transmutation that we're not we're not
adequately educated and trained to know
how to make right we don't know how to
alkalize our feeling of aimlessness our
feeling of vacuous 'no Swee don't know
how to commit
we transform that into something that
seems pregnant and electric and it's
that kind of training that we need right
now and so you know those people who are
equipped and I'm not saying I'm one of
them because I don't feel at all like I
am but those people who are equipped to
be able to step into the Fisher that's
opened by that boy by that void and then
to to present it properly to everyone
and to reveal the affordances that it
has the potential to cede us like that's
what that's what we need right now and
this could be I mean you know all the
doomsaying abound that we're hearing a
lot of it's justified perhaps some of
it's not but but what it could be
is it could be the opportunity for
intervention for a philosophic
intervention like philosophy has to come
out of it semi-retirement now and resume
its all post on the frontier and if it
can do that this might actually be an
opportunity the likes of which we've
never seen in our lifetime I don't know
I mean that could be revealed to be an
exclamation in a few weeks when all of
the settles down who knows but that's
the way I feel at the moment hmm well I
was just talking with my wife at dinner
time and we're talking about all of the
institutions that have are sort of
becoming into question at this point and
I mean school medicine you know
government the hole the hole all of the
structures that we rely on or that we
don't necessarily like but that we we we
work with unthinkingly they're not
collapsing but they're all being put
into question yeah all of them which
which just is it's a remarkable moment
in that sense
another thing that's being called into
question is and this is something that
Curtin guard was said had to be put into
question that we were going to wake up
his existential beings his common sense
busyness right living our lives
according to the obvious nosov common
sense and the busyness of our day to day
projects I had career guard said you
know and to
you and until you can wake up from that
and and he was deeply influenced by
Socratic aporia he wrote his
dissertation on Socrates and Socratic
irony until you can wake up from that
then there's a sense in which you can
never come into an authentic kind of
being and so I think Andrew I would take
your point I would deepen it by saying
that the way it's impacting on the
minutiae of our life as well not to not
to dismiss but to include as well as the
way it's impacting on sort of the
overarching you know the the gods of our
you know the institutions of our society
I think it's also important to note the
way it's impacting on the minutiae of
our life and therefore having the
capacity to wake us up from common-sense
obvious nests and the busyness and the
things that seem to be undeniable that
turn out to be actually quite deniable
like shopping yeah there's shopping and
like like going to school and like going
to work the most basic things right yeah
that John I have to sorry for
interrupting but when you were talking
about what you could gar says about this
and reminded of an anecdote I think it's
an offensive Samata or where it is but
it's somewhere in his corpus of work
that and this is where this is where the
importance of good humorists I think
come into effect at moments like this
but there's a there's a there's a little
anecdote where he says that and that
this is a fictitious and it's parent to
the kids but that you know he was going
about his business on the streets of
Copenhagen and he saw a man he saw a man
a busy man of his affairs was so
preoccupied with his busyness that he
had his head cast down walking around
going about his errands and he was run
over by a carriage and Kim Garst said I
laughed I laughed I laughed I laughed I
laughed because he was just so busy and
and I mean you know he has a he has a
slightly young slightly in fact a sense
of humor perhaps but I think the point
in here is that certain absurdities of
our of our everyday are now being
revealed in Contra right now and it's
going to take some good humorists and
irenna Slyke him
be able to spot them and to represent
them to us properly I find myself
laughing at myself for the things I take
very seriously and putting them into
question you know but also what gets
revealed is the stuff that should always
be taken seriously like the things that
people aren't questioning are the things
that they are retreating to almost like
the way you're supposed to take refuge
in the Sangha or the Buddha and the Sun
and the Dharma right they're taking
refuge in those practices and those
those people that give them you know the
senses of connectedness to themselves to
each other into reality they people are
withdrawing into the Citadel of whatever
religio they're capable of generating
and maintaining that's clearly the case
the monastery is coming to everybody's
home or something it's like its back and
and it's that well you know you've you
fate you face the life of a cop right
because police have lives that are 90
percent boredom shot through with ten
percent terror and so most of us are
facing that right now you know many
people are talking about you know
they're shut inside and they don't know
what they're gonna do with themselves
and on one hand they're facing this
tremendous kind of boredom and then but
then of course every now and then they
lift their eyes towards the window and
they're filled with a kind of terror and
the thing that modifies both of those
that enhances your capacity to find well
meaning in the face of boredom because
mortal boredom is sort of a mini meaning
crisis right and and the thing that
allows you to confront terror with
courage is is precisely your capacity
for cultivating meaningful relationships
with yourself with other people and with
the world and so the people who I think
are starting to sense this as not just a
momentary
disruption because that's not what it is
we should stop pretending that's what it
is this is a long-term thing we're
facing and the end and Jordan Hall and I
talked about this in a couple of recent
videos this is not going to be the only
pandemic all other conditions that cause
lists have not changed in the world in
fact if anything they're going to keep
increasing we're gonna keep melting the
permafrost we're gonna keep cutting down
the rainforests we're gonna keep
increasing our you know our travel and
our trade in grow in accelerating rates
this is gonna happen again and it's
gonna happen again and so the people who
are starting to realize that this is
could be something as game-changing
could not maybe not this time but I'm
but with increasing frequency the
probability of this happening is gonna
go up dramatically we're facing
something like what the Black Plague did
to Europe in the Middle Ages and how it
completely altered the worldview the
sense of agency and arena that people
had in a profound and irreversible
manner I think we're facing that I'd
like I say maybe not this pandemic but I
would predict within the next one that's
what this is maybe a minor pandemic for
one thing young people are not dying you
know absolutely terrible that elder
people are dying but I think in the
Spanish flu killed more people than
olive oil longer or one or something so
and I can having that every five years
yeah there's another thing that's been
kind of interesting about this
interesting and interesting in a
perverse way but our relationship to
time which already has been affected in
the way that Han talks about right the
third the aimless wizzy of time right
the effect that that has in our ontology
is also changing as a consequence of
that so for instance I find it
incredible in the proper meaning of that
term that a month ago or just over a
month ago I was I was traveling around
and I was in Italy for maybe about 10
days and then I came back you know
through a couple of its larger airports
more or less carefree coronavirus had
started at that point to permeate
consciousness but not knowing that it
has now and and certainly there was no
ordinance to self isolate when I got
back that was just over a month ago
the world has changed utterly since then
and and the the fact that such change
could be so comprehensive and so
instantaneous and every day every day
there's it's like there's this deepening
recurrence that makes the virus feel
cyclical like almost purgatorial right
see cuz for many of us has dwelled in
our consciousness for only a matter of
weeks and already it's starting to feel
inexorable and interminable like we've
been living with it for an eternity and
yet it's only been a few a few weeks so
the way that it leaders the way that it
rests on our consciousness seems not to
track our typical experience of time so
I think our our ontology of passage of
ours is also changing because of that
too and so you and the realization that
you were talking about John of the
transitory yielding to something
indefinite I think a lot of people
haven't quite crossed that threshold yet
but some people have and I think that
when a quick critical mass crosses that
threshold that terror is the thing of
all of all of the systems right economic
educational health etc of all of the
systems that are affected by this the
one that I'm most apprehensive about is
what happens when the critical mass
starts to realize that this may yet be
an indefinite state of affairs and that
our relationship to the world with the
fifth like the physiognomy of the world
the countenance of the world is slowly
slackening it's slowly starting to look
crestfallen and when that physiognomy
completely goes slack and loses its
confidence that's when that's like I'm
worried about it's like a judgment or
something it's like the last judgment
like I'm sorry to bring that up but I'm
thinking at all it's I think of like
some people are fully prepared in the
sense they're spiritually preparing
themselves and they have been for a long
time and other people will be just
totally unprepared I mean some people I
guess there's degrees of preparedness
but but but it almost feels like it
almost feels like this apocalyptic
biblical moments or something and but
notice that could notice that Antrim
notice that I think it's on Paul
recently I haven't seen the video yet
Paul vindicated one on whether or not
this is a judgment of God oh I just saw
it it's fantastic I don't like this
wonderful that's really good though I
imposed is so insightful II yeah well he
always does that that goes other
question so what I wanted to say Andrew
is notice how we are starting to shift
and of course all of the and and and it
should continue by the way all of the
political socio-economic and most
importantly the medical language is
still rolling but already the
mythological language is struggling to
come to the fore and you invoked it
spontaneously Andrew Paul's already
invoked it it's part of his job to
invoke their thoughts and I mean that as
a compliment there's any thoughts
appalled right and one of my concerns
one of my concerns is and I was talking
to this about Chris is that there's a
pattern that could could potentially
emerge in which this gives an initially
a spike in a sense of meaningfulness and
I was talking also with this with Peter
Lindbergh because when you can invoke
those terms seriously imagine being a
imagine three three months ago trying to
invoke judgment God's judgment and the
apocalypse right seriously and everybody
would have their eyes would have large
like me Chris and I've seen this when we
try to talk to people about this you're
always sort of glaze over and I know but
notice how now you can say that right
you know it all sincerity and you can
expect reasonably so to be taken
seriously so that mythological language
is coming out and notice what could i
khalaf i it a little bit okay it please
that's why you're saying I'm sorry I
interrupted I didn't I don't want to
miss the tribute everything to you but I
just wanted to say that you know I think
what's what's happening for a lot of
people is that you know the the virus
right it's it's it's it's taken on the
mythological and I mean that the sense
I'm trying to articulate the
mythological role of like an Old
Testament deity
the demonic chaotic aspect is out of the
blue unpredicted reality that will do
what it will do remember God's name I
will be what I will be right the the the
nameable thing that comes in and it's
ubiquitous like some sort of spirit and
you don't know who who has been taken by
it and who hasn't and it seems to be
falling as a judgment but you're not
sure what the judgment is and it seems
to be potentially assuring in a new a I
mean these this is a way of thinking
that you know is strongly associated
with like Old Testament deities and and
the thing about that is is the problem I
see with that is that has a lot of
potential danger associated with it as
the mythological meaning we try to bring
to bear uh-huh yes and so that's why I
maybe I interjected tumeric prematurely
and I apologize for that but I think
this is nevertheless an important point
to bring up well I want to say I want to
say that I don't think I wasn't
suggesting this is some kind of
punishment of God or any of that
nonsense like III that's that's
grotesque to me as a way of thinking
right what what it what it feels like
more is that some people some people are
going to suffer meaninglessly and other
people are going to you know have a
deeper experience of life after such an
event but why the term judgment then
because yeah it just came to me when he
was talking and he and and and I was I
was thinking of the the Old Testament
and I was thinking of this the final
days and all this sort of stuff where
some people make it into the kingdom of
heaven and other people don't so that's
not and that's not that's more
existential than and and I wouldn't want
to ascribe any kind of no no theism to
that even you know no I wasn't trying to
do that that's why I was very careful to
use the word myth you know what I'm
saying is right that language came very
naturally to you and what's what's
important is exactly the point you just
made you don't you don't hold to any of
the metaphysics
behind that language but nevertheless
that those images that have been woven
into our culture come spontaneously to
mind and I don't think that's happens
thanks Andrew I think that's going to
happen for a lot of people in a lot of
ways in a lot of circumstances and that
is risky because that's the kind of
thinking that can mobilize people in
whatever even some pretty weird ways
yeah yeah and so I think you can sort
cults and cults and prophetic calls the
cleansing and purity and purification is
that language so far away from where we
are now
it's not that far no no it's not because
I mean already into certain forms of
social intimacy are already appropriate
so actually no purity purity codes
abound right now and they may well they
may well persist in that direction but I
was going to say to Andrew that I think
that the the instinct to find a certain
amount of reflexivity to see a
reflection of ourselves born in the form
of the virus even though even if we're
not even if we're not subscribing to the
metaphysics behind behind behind divine
judgment if we're if it's done very
carefully the fact is that there is
something about the virus that is going
to pronounce and surface something that
is already implicit in our experience of
meaning right that's the whole point of
it being an analogic host for the
meaning crisis is that it is surfacing
like as a cathodic force bursting up
from the unconscious if you will it is
surfacing something that's already
present that's already present to us
that's already implicitly present to us
so obviously you know we have to be very
careful about metaphysical attributions
but using the virus as a dialectic way
of confronting our meaninglessness is
where the is where the pedagogical
opportunity of this comes from right not
simply to to wave it away to the
to the to the you know to the random
cruelty of nature even if that's what it
is fundamentally but rather not to pay
attention to what it - what it reveals
about our our the relationship or
ontology right that's not and that's not
a divine attribution necessarily but
it's it's taking the emergence of it to
be to be a symbolic affordance for
communing with ourselves yeah
individually and as a culture well I was
listening to this rabbi speak about it
and if you were if you were an Orthodox
rabbi and you believe that everything
that happened was God right you you
would think that this also is God right
and this is a divine thing that's
happening uh-huh because the Messiah is
coming and and and therefore you you
just have to keep sort of living your
life in in celebration and it's not that
oh this is this judgment and you're
being punished or or anything like that
that was the feeling I got from him as
like a person of faith and how they see
this and that doesn't take away from any
of the you know the pain and the
suffering and all that it's just I don't
know if I'm being very clear and what
I'm trying to say so it's almost the
opposite of what John was saying about
judgment is that it's not that people
are being judged
it's that reality is coming in and if
you were religious you would say divine
reality is here you know this is divine
reality I mean I'm okay with using the
word divine maybe you want to see sacred
but well I want to respond to that
because ishi I think what I'm saying is
we face a choice and I think the word
you invoked is the word that you know
Jordan Hall and I are talking a lot
about which is what does faith mean now
and what does it and is there is there a
sense of faith that can put us into the
the kind of situation we're in where
we're not talking about faith as the
attempt to bring about closure the
temp to two to reestablish and I'm using
Chris's sense of this word uncertainty
but faith is right because these are
these are you know and this is this this
is the fear I was trying to articulate
with the potential mythological
resurgence of sort of a demonic deity
the deities that will promise a
certainty and closure and purity and
protection right and that's I take that
as a very serious threat and I think one
of the responsibilities I feel now and
I've been privileged to work with Jordan
with that and also with Chris but two
videos with Jordan is well there's an
alternative way of understanding faith
that doesn't mean that seeking for
closure and completeness and purity and
perfection but instead is about a kind
of it's a cultivated sense of being that
gives you a continuity of contact with
things as they unfold so that you can
evolve with them and you have a sense of
the course of that so that you are
sensitive to Kairos and you can
participate in it in in with effective
agency that sense of faith rather than a
if you'll allow me this word a worship
based a sense of faith which is what I
was trying I'm trying to pull these two
things apart I'm not trying to deny
anybody their worship I you know what
that I don't do but what I'm trying to
say is for those of us who don't find
any kind of nostalgic return a viable
option and I would really really hope we
don't turn back to a demonic deity
answer um then we do need to re
articulate we need to bring up into
dialogue and into dialectic the kind of
faith that we started this discussion
with the faith that Socrates has when he
says the unexamined life is not worth
living how does he get that it's not
certainty in the way that two plus two
equals four it's not certainty but it's
a it's a he's in he's been he's lived
his life there's been continuity of
contact with an unfolding disclosure of
being that has vouchsafe to him what a
meaningful life is and he's sensitized
himself
and acquired that tastes deeper and
deeper and that's the kind of faith I
want to try and bring out the kind of
faith that is in measurably in meshed
with dia logos and that's what I'm
trying that's why I brought up that
whole concern that I had isn't that I
don't want any of that that mythology
that tends to like try to total eyes and
shut down and you know bring about the
the closure and the the completeness and
the purity and the perfection but we
need to resist that temptation and I'm
gonna use that biblical sounding word
deliberately and and the way we can
resist it and it's not just like trying
to hold it off we have to beautify and
fall in love with if you'll allow me
Socratic faith as a contrast to that
that that that I don't know what they
call it that demonic faith hmm Socratic
faith and demonic faith okay III think
the other John there's also there's also
a way in which the Socratic faith the
disposition of Socratic faith can
carefully and perhaps not collectively
but maybe on a person-to-person basis
the Socratic faith can be applied as an
attitude an interrogative attitude to
foster dialogue with the motifs with the
demonic motifs that instinctively
surface at times like this like totally
keep going but I just want to say right
all right great that's a really good
point that's an excellent point because
there's no there's no stopping the
perfusion of those of the of those kinds
of motifs I mean they're they're they're
baked so thoroughly into us at this
point that we're not going to be able to
wave them away or turn resolutely away
from them and ignore them but we are
going to have to find a way to bring
them into our die to enfold them into
the dialectical process and I'm thinking
very much in a in a sort of a union
careful calibrated Union descent into
the contents of the impersonal
unconscious right and that's exactly
what the whole process is about it's
it's it's you know I see I see you I see
you motif and I raise you you know let's
let's well that's what was worried about
with with just staying in this exercise
mode of angst and and that kind of thing
is that we have to dive into these I
don't know into the symbolic world on
some level and and and that takes a kind
of faith as well right yeah it does we
need to know how to turn the Old
Testament demon back into a Socratic day
Damon Socrates had as Damon and IIIi
think Chris's correction of my point is
completely correct and and wonderful and
and it's like the dialectic and that's
the pure dialectic that is expressing
here that we can't get stuck on this one
mode right Yee
apologies I interrupted you again it's
it's about how about I have when I get
accept we're all interrupting each other
it's fine I just okay I just wanted to
pull a nose I think what Chris just did
there was like not only correct I think
an example as you pointed out Andrew I
think very astutely it exemplifies the
very thing we're trying to bring to the
fore yeah I said there's a way Chris is
right I think there's a way of
addressing my concern but like I say in
a process of conversion and
transformation rather than a simple
process of exclusion I was falling prey
to the very thing I was criticizing I
was trying to trace remove decode and
keeping keeping something at bay which
is exactly the wrong thing to do so well
we could think of a non-theistic mode of
looking at the last at the Last
Judgement story or any of the old
stories and the Testament like but
they're not there to be understood in
some absolute as you say enclosed sort
of way right they're there to be worked
worked at and looked at as a piece of
sort of as a transparent window into
reality of some some kind the trick is
to keep them to I mean to keep enough of
the of the demonic within the demonic so
that it can challenge us and shake us up
because if we we need to be we need to
get into a place where we are open to
being surprised and shaken up because
that's what we're now facing going
forward in my estimation facing and and
if we might
if we try to domesticate this with the
demonic that's my concern but I like
Chris's idea that entering into a kind
of Union dialectic wicket so that we can
transform it into the Socratic demonic I
think that's I think that's a brilliant
insight Chris I think that's excellent
I personally idea of bringing young and
Socrates together because Socrates on
his own feels very dry to me and young
young is so rich nominal logically they
make they make a wonderful marriage of
heaven and hell well Chris and I are
gonna be working on a paper on that
actually probably probably like Monday
right yeah top of mind for us no I just
cuz I like the way that you've um I like
the way you've you've pinned it to a
catchphrase John to turn the demonic to
the demonic I think is oh I like that as
a nice pithy Turner phrasing yeah well
thank you so I I was trying to get a
turn of phrase that captured the turn of
your insight one thing that's been very
interesting for me to see in this
process it's funny I'm normally not much
of a news junky but of course I've
probably like most of the rest of the
world I've become one in these these
last days and sorry and the most recent
days I don't mean these last days maybe
that was a Freudian slip I don't but but
one thing that's been really interesting
and I mean we've you know we've talked
nauseam right now about about what the
the diminishment of our wisdom
institutions has done in a longer term
for our culture but one thing that we're
really seeing right now I find it
fascinating you know every day when the
politicians come out of their their
sanctum and have to address the public
and they they're forced into a position
of having to give platitudes and having
to give reassurance and aside from just
the practical and logistical messages
that they have to issue they're also
voiced with the demand of bringing calm
and bring
perspective now it's one thing to bring
calm to say you know folks we're doing
the best we can we've got it under
control but you can see them struggling
and I actually have I have sympathy for
them in this respect because that's
fundamentally it's it's it's in excess
of their role it's beyond their office
or at least it ought to be arguably it's
beyond their office to bring perspective
to bring the philosophic perspective to
what's going on but because we don't I
mean obviously for those beholden to a
certain faith and worship you know they
they round on their their clergy etc but
for those for now a sizable I mean
majority in the West maybe minority in
the world but still a sizable minority
in the world who don't have those
offices to turn to we're rounding on our
politicians to give us some if you give
us that perspective and there's I mean
and they obviously don't have it that's
not to say individuals among them can't
be insightful I'm sure they can but as
an office they just that's not only and
that's not the office they hold and I
think what we're starting to see right
now is we're starting to see that the
gap the vacuum the absence of the wisdom
institutions is particularly pronounced
at a time like this
you mean the separation of church and
state is is is is showing up as being
sort of schizophrenic
yeah well the church part is that is in
some ways absent altogether I mean
they're not they're not but but for for
many of us you know where our first
instinct is not in fact to look to
church leaders for perspective and and
we obviously look to our politicians to
give us the practical information we
need to know our business but between
those two things there is so fundamental
chasm within which we we we have only
ourselves to rely on but but this is
again where the context and this way you
have to have to be the dialogues with
the drama in the context Socrates right
you have to remember that when we're
reading these dialogues where they set
their set opens is literally under siege
people are walled in they are locked
down the city is under sieves the
Athenian Wars going there has been a
massive plague Pericles has died right
you know there's all that stuff is often
the context surrounding right the both
the dramatic context within which
dialogues are set in the historical
context in which Plato writes them and
they're originally presented Socrates is
very much he's not foreign to the
situation we are talking about
he is birthed out of it he is there in a
situation as you know as challenging as
threatening as we are in and that's why
he's again the the practice that he's
doing within that context that has not
happen stance that is not happenstance
and and again you know and he's he's
trying to steal his way steer his way
between you know various you know
political skill and Charybdis as as
athens careens around trying to find a
political solution to what many people
are now saying was ultimately you know a
cultural and you know a meeting crisis
for ancient heaven and he's supposed to
exemplify who we are supposed to be yes
moment is what you're saying
yes and and it's supposed to be Socrates
er that's what we're supposed to be
doing we're supposed to choose the life
the meaningful life the life worth
living because the choice really Andrew
I mean and that's what came out when I
was talking to ethos with us this
morning right the choice really I mean
initially initially first you know
Maslow's hierarchy I mean yes I get it
ish alia the choices live don't die yeah
but but that is not a sustaining choice
the choice is ultimately are you are you
living is it a good life you living
right is it is it a life worth living
III oh this is somewhat personal but I
decided and I've chosen and I've
committed to it I don't if it comes to a
point where I have to sort of start
violating the fundamental principles by
which I live in order to merely survive
I rather and I mean this I would rather
die I do not am I my own survival is not
as valuable to me
the principles that I that that you know
that I even that I've inherited from
Socrates that the unexamined life yeah
exactly
mm-hmm yeah yeah at some point people
wanna sorry I'm speaking I'm over
generalizing for my case uh out of hope
maybe miss borne hope but I suspect that
many people will come to where they
night might need to consider that desert
right
mmm-hmm and if I can come back to the
judgment again if you forgive me the
judgment is is maybe you live maybe
you'll die but the judgment is really
being able to say to yourself that
you've had a life worth living
yes so it's not it's not an imposed
judgment of some helpless person uh-huh
who doesn't have any say in what's going
on it's it's okay did I have judging am
I good you judge it we judge ourselves
right we we are judging ourselves not
the final judgment is is is is really
it's it's it's some gods on its from the
depths of design you know the being
whose being is in question okay and
ultimately have to we and we ultimately
have to live that question as deeply as
possible and and the way you live a
question is by turning it into a quest
nothing else you have to be open right a
quest is an open journey towards
continual revelation right and and I
just I think that what's gonna happen
once the the endurance aspect of it once
the emergency aspect of this is a little
bit more back rounded and the endurance
aspect comes out we have to go to have
to endure for a long time I think this
question about the resiliency of our of
the meaning of our lives is going to
become more pronounced as Christie and I
think that's I think that's the judgment
that and the word in here means in
French it means to make heard right yeah
you're something so good point
oh there's a point where we can't be
made hard right
that's right one level we need to be
made you know strong but not hard yeah
yes well it's and yeah and that's what
the storks are trying to get right again
I have a meaning I've been rereading
some of releases meditations and you
were saying at the beginning of this
conversation John that well you know
what's gonna happen increasingly as
people are going to retreat to those
relations that constitute them in most
instinctively and and at one point at
one point Marcus Aurelius effectively
enumerates a sort of he enumerates them
almost as a trinity of relations that
ground our sense of being right one is
to the vessel that envelops us the
second is to the sort of the divine
cause that the source of all that
follows all beings and then the third is
to those that live alongside us and when
I think about that I that's that's
that's a very comprehending Trinity of
relations then that we can use as a way
of refocusing ourselves at from a ground
that is that is fundamentally deeper
than the one that we're used to treading
on and your earlier you know the point
of living within the question of being
and questing after it is I think
precisely what you meant John by this
the definition of faith it's not closure
it's not the closing it's precisely the
opening it's the it's the opening of the
question that constitutes our being yes
it's the finite continually longing for
the infinite for the infinite is that a
strangle set yeah exactly and so the
point is it's it's the ongoing
receptivity to the emergence Jordan Hall
and I were both using the the the the
surfing and sailing metaphors right
where you're trying to set up outside of
kind of a passive empiricism or or an
overly active romanticism you can't
faith can't be in the imposition of your
will I'm just gonna make things happen
and faith can't be sort of the passive
waiting for the miracle that's going to
come and rescue you faith is like what
this what the what the what the what the
skilled sailor has it's the ability to
receive
and adjust and evolve and ride the edge
of the wave in the storm you know as
Andy Clark's book hazards you know
surfing the wave of uncertainty as we
eat or that's the kind of faith I'm
talking about which is whether and the
recurring realization that we are ever
and always beyond ourselves that reality
as ever and always beyond the
predicaments that confine us to the
present yes I was saying that your
definition of faith is the same thing as
well as your definition of wisdom faith
is wisdom in this in that sense yeah I
think so because because faith is
because it's because it's always
responding to to reality and not
shutting down and yet being flexible
enough to ya know be knocked over in
your sailboat and get up again and if if
yeah I would say if wisdom is connecting
you to the depths of your beings in the
depths of being so that you are
empowered that empowered nystagmus to
the depth that's the empowerment that we
I think we we seek from faith it doesn't
have our participatory knowing so
plugged in to how things are unfolding
that we can participate as fully as
possible yeah it's kind of also why
understanding that's good understanding
it in in the sense that you just meant
to John understand that's why power and
empowerment
unfortunately tainted though the word
now is politicized so the word now is
partaking of a something like an
exponent power I think for me is a much
handier way of understanding something
like a touch on it form for that very
reason yeah totally totally I guess I
drew an another way of bridging between
the meanings of faith and wisdom is that
the notion of reverence which is the
ability to you know to to sense the
relevance of that which is beyond you
appropriately to be appropriately fitted
to that which transcends your egocentric
framework and and give it a kind work at
what Iris Murdoch calls
a justice of attention that you give an
appropriate attention you give it the
attention it deserves to the degree it
deserves it knowing how to do that is a
profound kind of virtue Woodruff in fact
argues that reverence is a missing
virtue for us so I would sort of put
these together as overlapping and woven
you know referencing and faith when you
say when you say reference what comes to
my mind is worship and you hear you're
rejecting this idea of worship and and
I'm sorry and I I think reverence is not
quite enough because if you're revering
something you're still at a distance
from it if you're worshiping something
or if you find something divine if
you're something as sacred you're still
at a distance from it if something is
divine you know then if something if
it's something you worship then then
you're then you fall into it well so
that's just my minimal like that but I
want to challenge you because I might
think the appropriate the the way I want
to say that is that you know the
Socratic figure is actually supposed to
be the symbol on the sage is supposed to
be that which I mean that through which
we connect those we cross that distance
we don't collapse it how do we bridge a
right and and that's that's that's a
different thing
and what I mean by reverence I take your
point well and I'm not trying to invoke
worship we should have worship Socrates
I think that'd be ridiculous and you
find it horrifying but we worship kind
of we worship I used to worship Leonard
Cohen for example you know or my gay
friend Alexander right worship Bette
Midler and say she was divine you see
what I'm trying to say them I'm trying
to say that that that there's yeah
you're right we're both right in a way
like you're right to say yes we need
this sort of bridge yeah but I think the
bridge collapse is that at a certain
point when we're when we're fully
involved in what well I think we should
internalize the sage but we should never
be satisfied and that's what I'm trying
to get with the sense of being being a
feeling like you're you you realize the
relative
something right but that doesn't mean
you've you have you have conquered it or
consumed it like you we should
internalized I mean finally the the
quote comes to mind which is really good
although it presents it in a negative
way is Nietzsche's quote about Socrates
he said I hate Socrates he's so close to
me I'm always fighting him now that's
not worship but that's reverence man he
like he Socrates is so close to him he's
always fighting him Socrates is this
deeply deeply internalized challenging
figure and that's that's that's what I'm
thinking of right not that I so what I
think when I'm talking about reverence
I'm not I'm talking not about worship
I'm talking about that connectedness
exemplified in this age through this age
to something beyond this age that is
always going to be acknowledged to be
inexhaustible and beyond me what I'm
asking is the possibility of bringing
together intimacy and openness like you
should have with imagine somebody that
your that is your beloved right they are
close to you but you cannot enclose them
there's a difference there right and
that's what I'm trying to get I'm trying
to get that we have simultaneously the
with acknowledgement of how reality
withdraws and is beyond us but we can
nevertheless come into an intimate
flowing contact with it so that's what
I'm trying to get out with it the notion
of faith and reverence I'm yeah I'm
really not trying to articulate a kind
of worship or even putting off at a
distance but I don't also want an over
familiarization we need to keep the sage
and reality ultimately mysterious and a
tip-offs for us it's like a fire if you
get too close to it you get burned or
sight and so you got it you got to get
the Goldilocks zone where you're
intimate but the fire can still burn and
can still threaten you and say I mean
and this is why you know Greek myth
always pears the hero myth with the
hubris myth for all the myths of the
hero facing the challenge right there's
the hubris myth that don't fly too close
to the Sun right or don't you know
though
try and ride that the the chariot of the
Sun or don't compete with with act with
with Athena for being the greatest
Weaver you have all of these right
hubris because the point is yes you know
we should have we should come in too
close you know contact with the gods but
you know in even Plato said this you
know you should you to try and expect to
live there all the time is is a
ridiculous concern and so that's what
I'm trying to get out with the notion of
reverence that's why there's an eros is
that there's always the tin generis
implicit in that reference because it's
precisely because they are slacks
acquisition what they see in the thing
about eros is I mean this was it's a
mixture right it's both a lack and a
revelation and and Plato made it work
and you know in the symposium with
Socrates in eros how eros combines both
of those aspects together Russ wants us
to draw something into intimacy but eros
should also remind us of that which we
always lack and always will lie right
right yeah exactly
I guess so I guess that's what I'm
that's what I'm saying I think that the
air us like I I I understand the
difference between respect and reverence
as being that very difference that one
contains within it the disposition of
arrows and one fundamentally does not
yes
all right that's I think that's exactly
what I was trying to put my finger on as
long as we don't take just the current
meaning of arrows no no of course not
of course is it there a place also for
worship though I'm still I'm holding on
to this thing because it cuz I don't
know you you you if you're you you
worship let's say maybe you don't
worship the person themselves or the you
worship what they represent the you
worship the divine double or you worship
them hmm I don't know I guess it depends
what you mean by that word I mean I I've
already articulated that I think
philosophy is and this is a Socratic
Maxim is bound up with the combination
of a deep knowing of yourself and wonder
in which yourself is called into
question see you both coming engage on
the project and those are course and
separately bound up together
you can't deeply come to know yourself
and knowing yourself is always always
Socratic lee knowing the depths of the
world that you you belong to you can't
know yourself deeply unless you're also
capable of calling it deeply into
question and so wonder and awe i think
are inseparable from this project I mean
I think Plato in fact is part of the way
you can understand his whole
philosophical project is to engage in
dialectic so that we we afford via logos
and do logos will deepen wonder into awe
and then ah is for its own sake because
oh is that that state where we're
getting sort of the depths of ourselves
and the depths of reality resonating
with each other and a really powerful
and and and in its moving of its own
accord it's not at the direction of our
egocentric projects or desires so I
think if you mean by worship a seeking
out of practices that induce ah that
that's fine I don't have any problem but
maybe that's not what you mean by
worship and so I see worship is what
draws you out of your ISA egocentricity
towards our and then you can leave
behind the worship once you've arrived
at the off but it's but it's a stage
it's a it's a it could be and then it's
very Buddhist so and and I'm trying to
remain open to this and see I'm even
crossing my arms instinctively because I
go up I was brought about some
fundamentalist Christian and worship
doesn't meet what we're talking about
right now at all mmm-hmm means a kind of
fruitless and I mean that deeply a
fruitless kind of self-sacrificing
towards a God who seems to be nothing
but a a consummate narcissist who needs
endless praise and devotion while
telling us that we should never ever be
self-centered we should be like him but
what he seems to need more than anything
else is constant praise adoration and
worship and being put at number one no
matter what's happening at all costs in
all endeavors and I mean and I don't you
see and I feel privileged to have
experienced this or in a negative sense
of privilege because
that that I saw no good come out of that
in people's lives and it definitely hurt
and traumatized me in in powerful ways
and if that's what you mean by worship
then I yeah I I don't think that's what
I mean by worship is that many people do
mean that by worship many people sure do
I agree with you yeah mmm I take your
point
I'm sensing a lot of congruence between
what you're both saying I say I think
that there's there's a bit of a
terminological tension but I think
fundamentally what I'm what I'm getting
from you Andrew is that what you're
talking about with what you're meaning
by where it's correct me if I'm wrong I
think what you mean by worship is the
particular kind of relationship that the
person has with the symbol and and and
saying that the the particular
relationship that the person has with
symbol is precisely is precisely what
transfigures the entire ritual into some
of the features that John is describing
the Wonder and the awe and so you're
talking about it in terms of this the
interpersonal connection between the
individual and the symbol that they're
attending to as opposed to the uniform
the perceptual opening that's evoked as
a consequence of that relationship
fundamentally they cannot collapse into
the same praxis and that's why I think
fundamentally the two of you were
talking about is it's not exactly the
same at least continues I think you're
right I think that's a good way of
putting it and maybe we could
distinguish it this way there's an
idolatrous sense of worship and there is
an iconic not in person in a carbon
sense I was thinking about I can't I can
eyes him like how you would worship an
icon if you were a Christian Orthodox
person you had worship this icon as
being as being a symbol of the divine or
yeah and that and that's exactly what I
meant by the sage it brings you close
but also beckons you beyond and he never
allows you to it brings you close but
never allows you to enclose and and if
that's what you mean by worship and I
think Chris is right Andrew I think he
pointing to the convergence is exactly
right then I think that is a central
part of what we're talking about when
we're talking about Socratic faith and
what's happening that that what can
emerge when
emerges there's a deep reverence it can
be are inspiring and it may even become
symbolic in that worshipful way you're
talking about but what it shouldn't be
and I think it's what's clear Plato
continually undermines and what I had
the invective of from my own experiences
it should never become idolatrous
worship I also I also filled yeah I
think that's well said John I also feel
I also feel compelled to notice that for
some even though your particular
experience of ritual a Dori the ritual
adoration of Christ was idolatrous in
the way that it was forced on you for
for many Christians and I can't trap
myself among them but for many
Christians I and I trust this implicitly
because I know some of them very very
thoughtfully for for some Christians the
adoration is an iconic adoration and the
way that we've just described I I envy
them that but many of them many of them
have that experience for genuinely an
example he recorded know what I have the
opposite experience to John you know I
grew up without religion of any kind
right so everything you know I'm still
very very attracted to the esoteric
aspects of religion which lead into
mystery and not into this you know and
and I'm very I'm kind of critical about
the clinical Buddhists sort of where
aspect of Buddhism which doesn't have
worship which is is very let's say dry
and pseudo-scientific and psychological
and whereas I whereas and I'm also
attracted the Orthodox tradition because
because they there's this passionate
aspect to it but I can I can definitely
see how that can can go dark and and and
can it can be demonic and the opposite
of wisdom of any kind of yeah
but see what see what's happening here
see how I mean look what's happening
between the three of us yeah right the
deal logos the third factors emerging
none of us could have got here on our
own it's leading us in a way I'm finding
like things are being disclosed in a
powerful way and we're seeing how we're
inevitably being led into the depths of
religio and its in its deep relationship
although not its identity with religion
as we're trying to grapple with the
situation that's confronting us I think
this is exactly yeah Chris and I are
talking about yeah I and I love how what
what I am what I find I agree John and I
think that one way I think I think
Corbin puts it this way you currently
find wrong but I think that one of the
ways in which he phrases the
relationship of the individual to the
divine angel is that we are subjects of
the verb that is the divine angel and I
think that in the throes of diello go
like this I feel subject to a verb from
without in very much that way and and
you notice how your gesture was
automatic yeah I feel like I'm being
lifted up yes yeah and I'd be doing this
too like that being lifted up that uh
this is the point though Andrew
mentioned notice how the horizontal is a
meshed inexorably with the vertical with
a very now the two are just deeply
interwoven and on all we can
analytically talk about them as distinct
their dimensions
notice how phenomenologically and
functionally they are so interwoven
together yes and then our relationship
to them to add the another dimension to
that that that our relationship with our
relationship right now with the passage
of time also changes yes when we're
deeply immersed in us yeah and then also
to add the next this conversation notice
how much I've been alluding to other
conversations and you Andrew you and I
have had conversations and Andrew you
and Chris are like so that's that's
where this particular moment of
dialectic is sitting in this network of
all these other conversations that have
this kind of meta dialogue going on
between them because they're all
informing and constraining each other
right now right here right now and then
this dialogue will go into that network
of constraints on further conversations
mm-hmm right right like they're like
they're all they're all within the
Neoplatonic circle right they're all
yeah I thought of indras net but this
hacks perfect no I mean food science
notion of indras net is is totally
correct because if you read the depths
of patinas he independently comes to
this exact same metaphor that each form
reflects all the other forms and they
mutually reflect each other well so I'm
not familiar with this can you can you
bring your business like in a fractal
way you mean what's the what's this
analogy which one the net oh the net is
interest net is it's a Buddhist scholar
he he proposed the idea that that like
each each thing surrett the word isn't
quite right right
but each one every every hole on you
could say do you know this word hole on
each each part contains the hole or
contain a person or something like that
reflects its holographic in that each
the individuality of each is just how it
determinately reflects all the others so
there's each one is is right so this
jewel is just the reflection of all the
other jewels right okay okay so it's
like whiteheads notion of you know every
moment is the entire collapse of the
universe so the entire universe is
collapsing to that moment but that
moment is included in the collapse
towards this moment and so everything
it's really everything is mutually the
toe Hannah yeah well yeah and then
that's then Platonists clearly
explicitly articulates that also of how
the forms are related to each other
within noose no that's cool yeah but
whatever what a beautifully woven
metaphor well what's cool for me is I
think it's it's sort of this holographic
deep learning because what it is is it's
in this holographic multi-dimensional
compression and variation function
everything is compressing and then
everything is varying but it's not just
sort of like in in a neural networks one
oppression one variation everything is
compressing and burying for everything
else and so reality is like this an
amazing amazing holographic deep
learning network yeah right well I was
also thinking about to be just slightly
more prosaic about about Zack when we
talked with Zack he said that this was a
jam and there were three of us yeah and
you know we started I started off having
dyad like conversations with with John
and then the conversation and now it's
become a triad it's become a like the
Jimi Hendrix Experience or something
well you know I being the drummer and
I'm a bit wild and and and and John is
is sort of keeping us together and very
passionate and chris is maybe the bass
player it seems like it seems like a
kind of musicality and and that's that's
also what you're talking about when you
talk totally that's Christmas planning
yeah yeah this brought that metaphor to
the chapter we wrote in he played with
the musicality and me well Chris you
talked about it you know the in concert
metaphor that you that you made
throughout the chapter we just wrote
yeah yeah which is ironic because I'm
I'm in in my tactile life I'm not at all
very musical but it seemed to me that
there was no more there was no more
perfect analogy to play into the process
because because because the idea of
being able to I mean because it because
it because it both because it's both
concentrated and distributed at the same
time because a melody can recur and
because a melody can transform and a
melody can be present in all kinds of
different ways yeah it's just a most
perfect ahead John I just wanted that to
the metaphor now Andrew your metaphor
you know in jamming you have to pick up
on it you have to pick up on it but you
have to get you have to get pick up on
it and get clear up in it
right and if you try and hold on to it
too long you destroy it this is back
again to this fake the sense of faith
you know you know you're getting picked
up they're on it you're you're the
continuity of contact you can continue
to play the serious
play and that's again the Socratic faith
so we could actually add that to the
two-year metaphor Chris I've also
noticed
notice that it starts off much more
intellectual or more prosaic and a bit
awkward and and in many directions and
then we build towards this kind of a
penny of this vector it seems to happen
in all these kind of conversations least
ones I've been having we build towards
this we build up towards you know an
insight and a static insight of some
kind
yep and I think that's the third factor
that we were talking about that third
factor where it takes on a life of its
own and it instead of you pushing the
conversation forward it takes on a life
of its own and everybody has drawn up
together forward in it that's the third
factor it's like it's the spirit of the
conversation it's the Geist yes yeah
that you're taught you're spoken by the
conversation so transected yes detective
sensation exactly this is why don't you
logos and dialectic are so central not
only to you know the the ongoing issue
of the meeting crisis but in turn for
giving people the place and the presence
and the and and the in the interlocutors
to cultivate the kinds of responses we
need right now in the face of what we're
facing again
Socrates was in Athens during the plague
and while it was literally under siege
so we all have to be Socrates you know
well yeah in a way anyway we all else we
only in a way I'm sorry that felt very
banal actually a banal statement it felt
like a oh no I'm sorry
well he's even now advertising jingle or
something well yeah I don't want it to
become trivialize but I want I would
want to say we all have to become
Socrates but also in the way in which we
all have to become Siddhartha and we all
have to become loud say and perhaps if
it's not too sacrilegious given my
previous invective
you also have to become Jesus I mean you
have to recover Socratic wisdom and
faith we have to recover that Jesus is
agape we have to recover loud says--
flow we have
recover you know sit hardness capacity
for profound transformative insight we
need all of these now we needed all of
these and if art you know if our musings
about this stand outside of literalism
which of course they do then then I
don't think it's I don't think we're
blaspheming to say that that we have to
I don't think I don't think it's a
trivial statement and your to say that
we have to be Socrates because the way
that Socrates is Socrates you know I
trust you'll both take this in the in
the intended meaning even Socrates is
not Socrates yes yes so yeah in a way
that's that's precisely right we have to
be Socrates in the way that Socrates is
and is not Socrates precisely this is
never beyond himself I hope that's not I
hope that's not you reckon so that
himself if he said what he asked whether
he said you know I've given you a
Socrates more beautiful yeah yeah that's
right the historical Socrates because he
was much more concerned to represent
what Socrates lived for than what
Socrates was historically you know again
instead of pursuing this to the
historical certainty of Socrates Plato
was much more interested in getting us
to confront the truth of Socrates or the
as a form of Socrates does it work there
we go Andrew the essence the form and
the truth of satis yes and we have to
end this I was also thinking about the
meaning of you know Carl Jung talks
about imitation of Christ is is not
imitating Christ's life but it is
becoming more truly not ourselves but
our I guess the I guess our divine
double like you keep using that if
bringing that that was it the my last
question and that keeps coming up at the
end of these conversations as well this
notion of the divine double which I
talked about with Zack as well and and
the divine double being our potential
and our plurality and it's enacted now I
mean it's simple it's symbolically
already active in how it calls us forth
from our current self yes
and yeah I think the I mean part of what
I want to work on with Chris's I think
there's a deep connection between wisdom
the sense of faith Socratic faith and
being in the correct kind of
connectedness and identity with your
sacred second self which which also is
more or less which is which is very
convergent with the idea of being in the
right relation to your whole self in the
Union sense of self right to find the
midpoint of personality that Jung talks
about to be in relation with yourself
such that you're you're you it's
reciprocal and equilibrated third spirit
and transfer or I might say translucent
loose distance distanced in just the
right way that you are you are you are
you are not susceptible to to two
pathologies of inflation and overt
identification or God likeness but but
that you are that you are positioned
you're positioned you know in proportion
to your to your psychic potential
properly and I think that's very much
very much very if not I don't want to
make an argument from exact identity
here but I think I think the convergence
is pretty unmistakable yeah I would
agree with that I would agree with that
mmm-hmm I should get going soon so it's
it it's just this feels like what we've
also come to a culmination point in the
conversation mm-hmm
yeah yeah what do you think does anybody
else want to say anything or I don't
want to foreclose but I like I said I'm
already sort of half an hour past where
I said I would yeah well I wouldn't end
this I I would never end this it's such
a great pleasure for me and I appreciate
it so much but but there has to be an
end somewhere so well it's one of the
only things I like from Sartre you know
you said you never he talked about books
he said you never finished them you just
abandon them I don't think just abandon
them because we have other commerce the
conversation will continue
well that's part of what we were talking
about towards the end at Austin
yeah it's what's moving forward to
whatever it will become and I also there
was one point in their conversation
where I felt this is so important
I just wish like one person out there
could hear it there's just I don't even
remember what the point was but but
there's something really really
important in this conversation I mean I
mean there's a lot of things that are
really really important but even just
getting a little little piece of that
meaning could change everything I mean
does that make any sense am I being too
dramatic here no no no I think that's I
think that's that's that's that's
perfectly appropriate one thing you can
do to help that is as you've done before
and I've been slowly up low I was gonna
upload our second conversation this
weekend but I thought that the
conversations with Jordan Hall were more
you know we're more appropriate given
their their subject matter like you send
me the files from this conversation I'll
upload it onto my channel and promoted
of course yeah and I'd love to talk to
you again
Christopher sometime and likewise Andrew
anytime I mentally thank you and thank
you for having just having the having
the wherewithal to actually bring us
together and to organize it and just
like I feel I feel like I'm in I'm
indebted to the to the initiative that
youth that you've shown in all of this
and the delicacy and just the good taste
and good sense that you've shown in all
of this thank you you're so you're so
important to all of this Andrew and I'm
really that variable I don't rate for
you and grateful now to have to know you
and I'm I'm grateful for all that you're
doing yes thank you thank you so thank
you so much that's that means a lot to
me that you that you would say that and
I think you guys are doing the deep
scholarship and and you know hopefully
I'm helping to communicate some of your
ideas and get it get them out there and
I think they will be meaningful to
people and that's my hope and wish I
wanted to also thank
for the work that he's doing with
guy-guy cents doc reading through the
chapter and then trying to exemplify
idea logos by going through the Platonic
dialogues I think that's just an
invaluable resource and I'm like I'm
just very very grateful to be done so
thank you Chris for that well you're
you're another one supplies that lies at
the heart of all of my all of my
dialogic reading so it says there's no
there's no none of this without you job
you know that's true mm-hmm well I'm
looking forward to diving into that and
and I think I get my news from from you
guys you guys are like the news rather
than the other news that's going on this
is like the real news so thanks a lot in
and be well and take care and good
health to you and your families and all
that you to enjoy yeah well and be safe
and John needs him all the ones you love
yeah thank you so much guys have a good
one okay you take care